<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Reasons for a Generall Assemblie</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1638</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 17 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11761</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22054</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116984</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852199</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852199</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17509</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11761)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17509)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1291:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Reasons for a Generall Assemblie</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by G. Anderson],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Edinburgh] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>in the year of God, 1638.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B² .</note>
                  <note>In this edition, A2r line 4 of text has: nation.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of Scotland --  History, (17th century) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of Scotland. --  General Assembly --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17509:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17509:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>REASONS <hi>FOR</hi> A GENERALL <hi>ASSEMBLIE.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>HEBR. X. 25.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Forſake not the aſſembling of your ſelves together, as the manner of ſome is, &amp;c.</p>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <q>A VIRTVTE ORTA OCCIDVNT RARIVS</q>
               <p>
                  <date>
                     <hi>June</hi> 29. 1638</date>
               </p>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed in the year of God, 1638.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:17509:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17509:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>REASONS FOR A generall Aſſemblie.</head>
            <p>GOD by the light of Nature informing all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones and ſocieties to ſtudie their owne pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, teacheth alſo the particular kirkes of a nation, as the members of one bodie, to draw together into a conſociation, or repreſentative meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, for the preſervation of the whole, which cannot be ſufficiently procured by the particular care of Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, Presbyteries and Synods; they being but parts thereof, and no more independent and abſolute in themſelves, then particular corporations civile are in reſpect of the whole kingdome: So that by Natures light, the Parliament is not more neceſſarie for the eſtates of a kingdome, then is a nationall Aſſemblie for the particular kirks of a kingdome.</p>
            <p>The Son of God, the King and Head of his Kirk, hath gratiouſly promiſed, where two or three are ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together in His Name, there Hee will bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the mids of them; which doeth als well prove the Divine originall of nationall Aſſemblies to be keeped in the caſe of the urgent neceſſitie of the Kirk, as of other inferior meetings of the Kirk: And therefore the Councels of old uſed this for their warrand, and the Fathers being conveened in Councells, uſed to pray for <pb facs="tcp:17509:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>the preſence and aſſiſtance of Chriſt upon this ground of his gratious promiſe.</p>
            <p>The holy Ghoſt filling the hearts of the Apoſtles, moved them to conveene in a councell at <hi>Jeruſalem Act:</hi> 15. Whether alſo did reſort the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> by revelation at the ſame time,
<hi>Gal:</hi> 2.1. For keeping that Aſſemblie, as both ancient and moderne Divines obſerve upon that place, for which cauſe, and for the aſſiſtance of the Spirit which brought them together, they were confident to give out their determination in this manner: It ſeemed good to the holy Ghoſt, &amp; to us.</p>
            <p>The Chriſtian kirk directed by the light of nature, confident of the promiſe of Chriſt, and warranted by the divine practiſe of the Apoſtles, hath in all ages, even when ſhee was perſecute by the powers of the world, uſed this as the ordinarie and neceſſary meane for uniforme eſtabliſhing of Religion and Piety, for cenſuring of Hereſie, and for removing of ſcandals, and ſuch other evils as by Divine providence and predicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on muſt be, and would certainely bring diviſion, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation upon the kirk, if by this powerfull remeady they were not cured and prevented. Both Popiſh and reformed Divines agree in this truth: That although God by his omnipotencie, or by way of miracle may preſerve his Kirk on earth without Aſſemblies, yet in the ordinary providence of God, Aſſemblies are neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for the right governing and well being of the Kirk.</p>
            <p>Acording to this Divine right the Kirk of <hi>Scotland</hi> keeped her generall Aſſemblies with great evidence of the preſence and bleſſing of God from heaven; For while they continued in their ſtrength (far contrary to that which we have ſeene of late) the doctrine was
<pb facs="tcp:17509:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>by them preſerved againſt error and hereſie, the worſhip was keeped pure againſt ſuperſtition and idolatrie; the Diſcipline was holden in integritie againſt confuſion and tyrannie; unitie &amp; peace was entertained againſt ſchiſme and diviſion; piety and learning were advanced againſt profanitie and idleneſſe, every man had his gift ſtiried up and increaſed, every gift was made uſe of as it might ſerve for the good of the kirk; and all went from theſe aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies with freſh reſolutions, and fervent zeale for the worke of God in their particular places.</p>
            <p>The libertie of this kirk for bolding aſſemblies was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo acknowledged, and ratified by acts of Parliament, as is manifeſt by the letter ſent from the Aſſemblies to the Earle of <hi>Morton</hi> than Regent, in March 1573. And by the act of Parliament in the year 1592. For ſuch neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary cauſes as are expreſt in theſe acts, which being ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glected, religion could not be preſerved. King <hi>James</hi> as at diverſe other times, ſo by his Commiſsioners at <hi>Lithgow,</hi> in the year 1606. did acknowledge that the keeping of generall aſſemblies was the moſt neceſſary meane for preſervation of piety and union, and for exterminati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of hereſie and ſchiſme, and therefore willed that the act of Parliament for conveening the generall Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblie once in the year ſhould ſtand in force. The pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats themſelves in their aſſemblie at
<hi>Glaſgow</hi> 1610. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly acknowledged, that the neceſside of the Kirk did require yearly generall Aſſemblies, and the act of that aſſemblie did ſuppoſe and import the ſame: for by the Act they were made lyable to the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the generall Aſſemblie in their life, office, and benefice in generall, and in ſome particulars ſpecified therein, as that of the proceſſe of excommunication.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17509:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The cauſes noted by Divines for the utilitie and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie of Councels are many, As 1. For ſuppreſſing hereſie &amp; controverſies about points of doctrine: 2. For redreſſing abuſes and enormities: 3. For appointing, reſtoring, or preſerving the Diſcipline of the Kirk: 4. For the peace of the Kirk and for unitie: 5. For the mutuall comfort and benefite which the Godly may finde in their meetings, by ſtirring up, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainting one another with the ſtate of their particular kirks: 6. For the confirmation of doubting mindes in the trueth: 7. For keeping faithfull Paſtors in their places, thruſt out by their adverſaries, perturbers of the Kirk: 8. For puniſhing of heretickes, or ſuch as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce novations in the Kirk. Any one of thoſe may bee a ſufficient cauſe of conveening a generall aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly: But at this time not one or two, but all of them in a concurſe may be heard, crying for ſo neceſſarie a remeadie: For 1. The doctrine is corrupted by
<hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minianiſme</hi> and Popiſh errors. 2. Abuſes and enormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties through the governement of prelates are multiplied: 3. The Diſcipline of this Kirk eſtabliſhed, by the acts of aſſemblies and by ſolemne oath, is not only per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, but overturned: 4. Peace and unitie in the Kirk is turned into ſchiſme and diviſion, by the adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, who have minded nothing but their worldly peace, and increaſe of their dignities: 5. Brethren of the Miniſterie are become ſtrangers one to another, their mindes filled with ſuſpitions, and none of them bettered by another, more then if they were Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in ſundrie kingdomes: 6. Many of the people have for a long time doubted of their religion, not knowing what hand to turne to, when they found
<pb facs="tcp:17509:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſuch diverſitie of opinions amongſt Paſtors. 7. Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Paſtors have beene thurſt out of their Miniſterie through uſurpation of the prelats and their adherents, who take the greater libertie, and boldneſſe to ſmite their Fellow-ſervants, that there bee no generall Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies to controule or cenſure them: 8. <hi>Armini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> and popiſh teachers both in Kirks, and ſchools are rather rewarded and preferred, then cenſured and controlled: And therefore except Wee will ſuffer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion to expire, and the Kirk of Chriſt to periſh by conſumption or by combuſtion, Wee muſt reſolve upon the neceſsitie of generall Aſſemblies.</p>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Objections anſwered.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THE name of the Kirk belonges to the prelates, and the meeting of Our prelats for matters of religion is the repreſentative Kirk of this kingdome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The prelats cannot bee our repreſentative Kirke<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1. Becauſe they are not office-bearers of this Kirke, which ſince the time that the office of biſhops was aboliſhed, hath never to this day acknowledged any ſuch office, as is now exerced by them. 2. Although the office of our prelats had beene receaved by this Kirk, yet can they not be eſteemed the Kirk repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentative, ſince both in the Apoſtolick councell, <hi>Acts</hi> 15. and in many other councels afterward, Presbyters had their voces, and the ſpirits of the Prophets muſt be ſubject to all ſuch as by gifts and calling are prophets: <pb facs="tcp:17509:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
3. Becauſe they have no more warrand by the lawes of the countrey and Acts of the Kirk to repreſent the Kirk, then ſome few citizens, turning robbers, have to repreſent the corporation of the city, or ſome ſmall fiction ryſing in a kingdome againſt the funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall lawes, to repreſent the whole kingdome, or an impoſtume growing on the bodie, and making it diſeaſed and monſtrous to repreſent the bodie: 4. It is manifeſt by the acts of Parliament and Aſſemblies, that this kirk and kingdome never acknowledged any other kirk repreſentative ſince the reformation, but the generall Aſſemblie orderly conſtitute of Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionars, choſen and delegate for that effect. 2. The Service book, and new Canons repreſent to all men, what concluſions wee may looke for from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, if they were acknowledged to bee the kirk re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentative: And Wee may ſafely ſay of them, if they were the kirk repreſentative, what is by all our Divines affirmed of the Romane repreſentative kirk, made up of the members of the Romane hierarchie, that it cannot be the true kirk.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Where the Chriſtian kirk liveth under an unchriſtian Magiſtrate, Aſſemblies of the Kirk muſt be keeped, (according to the cuſtome of the Kirk for many yeares) without the conſent of the Magistrate: But where the Kirke liveth under a Chriſtian Magiſtrate, ſo that the kirke and Commonwealth make but one corporation: the Aſsemblies of the kirk muſt depend upon the indiction of the Prince or Magistrate, who is the head of the repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blick, and the principall member of the kirk.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wee humblie acknowledge that the ſupreme Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate hath power to indict the Aſſemblies of the <pb facs="tcp:17509:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>kirk, and when in his wiſedome he thinketh it conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient, he may by his authoritie conveene aſſemblies of all ſorts, whether generall, provinciall, presbytries, or kirk Seſſions: But the queſtion is, whether he may prohibite or impede them, when the neceſſities of the Kirk evidently call for them. 2. No man will thinke that a republick, becoming a Chriſtian Kirk, ſhould loſſe any of her civile liberties, why then ſhall a kirk being in her ſelfe a perfect republicke, although of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother kinde, becauſe ſhee now lives under a Chriſtian Magiſtrate, loſſe her priviledges, or ſuffer diminution in her Chriſtian liberty, whereof the holding of aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies is a neceſſary part: 3. When the Chriſtian Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate either forbiddeth, or in the urgent neceſſity of the Kirk forbeareth to conveene Aſſemblies; in this point the Kirk is left to her own libertie, and muſt provide for her own ſafetie. 4. The great wiſedome of Ieſus Chriſt, the King of the Kirk, hath provided ſufficient ſupplies for all her neceſsities, and fitting re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies for all her evils, of which there be many that cannot bee helped without generall Aſſemblies; and therefore, not only the Chriſtian Prince, but the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors of the Kirk, eſpecially when the indiction cannot be obtained of the Prince, are bound as they will anſwer to Chriſt to provide that the Eccleſiaſticke republick receave no detriment, and to eſteeme the ſafetie of the Kirk to be the ſupreme law.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Although the libertie of the Kirk for holding aſſemblies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ence in the year at leaſt, and oftener</hi> pro re nata,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Object.</hi> 3.</note> 
                  <hi>be ratified in the Parliament</hi>
1592. <hi>yet the act of Parliament</hi> 1612. <hi>acknowledgeth the indiction of the generall aſſemblies to <pb facs="tcp:17509:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>pertaine to his Majesty by the prerogative of his royall crowne, and therefore abrogates the former act.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>God forbid that any man ſhould be ſo impious,<note place="margin">Anſ.</note> as to thinke that his Majeſties royall prerogative doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine or import any thing contrarie to the royall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative of Chriſt, by whom Kings reigne, or to the liberties granted to the Chriſtian Kirk, whoſe nurſe fathers Kings on earth muſt be; the matter therefore may be eaſily ſalved without wrong to the Kings Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, or to Ieſus Chriſt the King of Kings, and to his Kirk by this threefold diſtinction. The firſt which is uſed in the point of calling Aſſemblies both by Popiſh and reformed Divines, putteth a difference betweene a ſolemne and publicke indiction, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ia citationis ac pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licae authorizationis,</hi> by way of citation or compulſion by authoritie; and between a voluntarie meeting, <hi>Per viam admonitionis ac requiſitionis,</hi> by way of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an admoniton or advertiſement; the former is ſo proper to the King by his prerogative, that it can neither be given to the Pope, nor to any forraine power, nor with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out uſurpation can be claimed by any of his Majeſties Subjects. <hi>Moſes</hi> only may blow the trumpet; The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is proper to the Kirk and her office-bearers, which neither is, nor can be taken from her by any Act of Parliament. Secondly we are to diſtinguiſh betweene a cumulative or rather a poſitive power of calling Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, and betweene a privative or deſtructive power, The former is acknowledged by the Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament to belong to the King, who being <hi>Custos
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triuſque tabulae,</hi> may, and ought, <hi>pro re nata,</hi> call the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies of the Kirk, but the other cannot be meant in the act of Parliament 1612. 1. Becauſe it doeth
<pb facs="tcp:17509:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>not confer any new power, but only declareth <hi>quo jur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> his former power of indicting (which is only ſet down in the act 1592.) doth appertaine to him: 2. Becauſe in the act 1592. it was found that the Kings power of indicting generall aſſemblies, and that by vertue of his prerogative royall, might conſiſt with this native li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie of the Church, to appoint the time and place of her neceſſare aſſemblies, in caſe of the Kings not uſing his prerogative by appointing them: and the act of the Kings prerogative was declared to conteine no derogation to the liberties and priviledges granted by God to his Church, whereof the libertie of generall aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies is there acknowledged to be one. 3. Becauſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though <hi>Cujus eſt nolle, ejus eſt &amp; velle,</hi> it is not alwayes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciprocall, <hi>Cujus est velle, ejus eſt &amp; nolle,</hi> and 4. becauſe the act of <hi>Glaſgow</hi> aſſemblie, whereof the act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is ratificatorie, acknowledgeth the neceſsitig of yearlie generall aſſemblies.</p>
               <p>Thirdlie, We muſt obſerve the difference betwixt the indiction, or calling of aſſemblies conſidered abſolutelie, and in reſpect of the circumſtances of time and place, <hi>Indictio ſimpliciter,</hi> and <hi>ſecundum quid,</hi> the act of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament intendeth no further but touching the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancess of the place, as in what town the aſſemblie ſhall conveene, and of the time in what Moneth of the year, and what day of the moneth, as is evident by the act of 1592. which giveth this libertie of time and place to the aſſemblie, when the Kings Majeſtie or his Commiſsio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner doth not appoint them.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
